WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Come on. Move along. This way.
Downstairs.
I hope everything will be resolved
while we're away.
How is she?
It breaks my heart to see her in
that place, but she is strong.
Ah, Barrow.
It's good of you to take this on.
Isn't it, Bates?
It's good of you to allow it,
m'Lord.
Lord Sinderby has rented Brancaster
Castle for the grouse.
The house is extremely grand
and knowing Lord Sinderby
everything will be done
~ in the most lickety-split manner.
~ I think I'm up to it, m'Lord.
~ I've started packing in the dressing
room. ~ According to Lady Rose,
he's taken his own butler,
which I cannot think wise
as it will only cause disruption.
So you'll need to be on your toes.
The train is at 11 tomorrow morning.
Bates will pack, you should watch.
~ And now I think I'll leave you
to it. ~ M'Lord.
Miss Baxter, I'll help you pack.
You've a lot on your plate.
Thank you, Mrs Hughes.
I could do with a hand.
But I've talked with Lady Mary
and Lady Edith.
It's hard to cope with three ladies
at once,
what with tweeds, evening dresses,
tea gowns and all.
Tea gowns?! We're not in the 1890s
now, Mr Molesley.
More's the pity.
Did she take a cake with a file
in it?
I don't know why you're making such
a fuss.
You'd visit Denker if she were
locked up.
Only to check if the locks were
sound.
Bates was found innocent, no
doubt Anna will be, too.
Lord knows they don't deserve their
luck, those two.
I heard from Rosamund - she says
she's going to try to get to the sale
~ of the della Francesca.
~ I'm glad we'll be represented.
~ Pity it clashed with your trip, or
you could have gone. ~ I don't mind.
I've said goodbye. If you will
excuse me, I must dash off.
~ I'm expected in York at 3:00.
~ You should have gone with Mary.
~ You could have given her lunch.
~ I didn't want to kick my heels
before my appointment.
Do you have any plans
for when we're away?
Shrimpie's men have found Princess
Kuragin.
~ When she arrives in England,
she's coming straight to me. ~ What?
~ When did you hear?
~ Yesterday.
We've got her out and brought her
to safety.
~ You must be looking forward
to seeing her again. ~ Hardly.
If you don't like her, why have you
sent Shrimpie to her rescue?
That's what I keep asking.
~ Well, Granny?
~ Oh, you know me.
Never complain.
Never explain.
You don't usually have much trouble
complaining.
(Did you give a false name?)
Certainly not.
(But suppose it comes out in the
papers you came to see me.)
It will show that the Crawleys do
not believe you did it.
Yes, but...
who knows what they'll come up with
before they're done?
~ What do you mean?
~ I've been here before with Mr Bates.
They weave their web with little lies
and innuendo
~ until they hold you fast.
~ Anna.
All they have is one man who thinks
he saw you.
That's not enough.
Any character witness could prove it
isn't in your nature.
And you know we would all testify to
that if it comes to it.
(I assume you know about Lady Mary's
visit this morning?)
~ I do.
~ (I don't like it.)
(Suppose it gets into the papers.)
'Earl's loyal daughter visits maid in
prison.'
I should think the public would like
her for it.
Whether they do or not, I hate to
give them the chance
to poke their grubby noses into our
business.
What on earth's going on here?
Shouldn't you be in the gun room?
Mr Jackson's got the underkeeper
with him.
~ I didn't want to be in their way.
~ You're in OUR way.
It won't take long. I'm glad of
the chance to check it's in shape
~ before they go.
~ I don't need checking.
I'm to load for His Lordship,
which you never can.
Mr Barrow's father was
a shooting man.
Killing sparrows by the gasworks is
not the same as shooting grouse
at Brancaster Castle!
~ Must have been hard to miss your
visit. ~ Lady Mary wanted to go.
They allow one visitor at a time,
unless there's a special reason.
It may help for them to see the
family thinks her innocent.
The sacrifice could be worth it.
I'd cut my arm off if I thought it
would do any good.
I don't think that'd be sensible. We
can't have you wobbly at both ends.
They didn't finish this,
and they're away tomorrow,
so I thought we might.
~ It's a favourite of mine.
~ Mmm, it's very nice.
You won't go far wrong
with a Margaux.
Mmm!
These four are real contenders.
Three good-size bedrooms, bathroom
already installed
~ and a room off the kitchen for
a maid. ~ Mm.
Where's the butler's pantry?
If we're offering bed and breakfast,
~ there should be someone there to run
it. ~ Oh, I don't know.
We should go and look at them,
and then we'll talk.
Is it worth speaking to Murray again
before we go?
Why can't he get her out?
He says they've uncovered something,
but they won't tell him what.
What did Susan have to say for
herself?
She's furious we've been invited and
she hasn't.
~ How did she find out? ~ I told her.
I didn't want her to hear it
from someone else.
The divorce would be a big thing
for Lord Sinderby to get over.
~ Cars are ready, M'Lord.
~ Thank you. We're just coming.
What's the matter? What were you
doing at York? I wish you'd tell me.
Nothing worth bothering about.
Are we all here?
Where are the children? Nanny said
she'd bring them to say goodbye.
They'll be outside.
George, come to Mummy.
You, too, Marigold, come to...
~ .. me. Come on, darling.
~ Bye, bye, Daddy.
Did you see that? Edith wanted to
say, 'Come to Mummy,'
but she stopped herself just in
time.
~ Still sure I shouldn't have it out
with her? ~ Quite sure.
It's not our secret.
Check every piece of luggage
when they're transferred in York.
I have changed trains before,
Mr Carson.
I'm impressed you should come
to say goodbye, Mama.
Why do you always talk of me
as if I were a salmon
who laid my eggs in the gravel
then swam back to the sea?
You're very maternal, Granny,
if it suits you.
~ When does Princess Kuragin turn up?
~ Tomorrow.
~ What about the prince? ~ He'll be
coming to dinner that night.
~ Will you be there?
~ Would I miss it?
I can't tell you how sorry
I am that we will.
Get aboard before I get cross
with you.
All aboard!
It's all in your hands, Carson.
May they prove worthy of the charge,
my Lord.
Lord Sinderby, Branson and Barrow -
not what I'd call a recipe for a
peaceful week's shooting.
Makes you wonder what they'll be
shooting at, by the end of it.
So, Daisy, what are you working at
while they're away?
~ I haven't decided yet.
~ You don't sound very keen.
To be honest, sometimes I'm not sure
I should go on with it.
I mean, what am I trying to prove?
~ We're not having another crisis,
are we? ~ No.
But the more I think about it,
the more I wonder how realistic are
my plans.
Wouldn't it make more sense now to
get on with my life?
Mrs Patmore, what are you doing in
here?
Oh, I came up for a bit of air.
It's nice to get your head above
ground for five minutes.
~ For Rose's sake, we must all be on
our best behaviour. ~ I agree.
Sinderby always looks as if he's
spoiling for a fight,
whether he is or not.
We must be careful not to give him
grounds for one.
I wonder if I was right to come.
I don't want to sound like Larry
Grey,
but I'm not Lord Sinderby's idea of
a perfect son-in-law.
Stuff and nonsense! We Crawleys
stick together.
For once I agree with Mary. You'll
enjoy it when we get there.
Besides, you're a good shot.
Any host will forgive a lot if
you get the numbers up.
~ What is it? Can I do anything to
help? ~ Yes, stop fussing.
I suggested to Nanny she take the
children to Lake Gormire for a
picnic.
Do you think it too dangerous?
Shall I telephone to cancel it?
~ Why don't you shut them up in a box
in the attic, let them out when
they're 21? ~ Don't be unkind!
Honestly, I'm the mother round here
and I'm not panicking.
(Hmm.)
~ So, everything's under control?
~ I'd say so, m'Lord.
The housekeeper has drawn up the
list of rooms.
How do you find the servants
generally? Are they co-operative?
They'd rather be taking orders from
their own butler.
I'd rather be giving them to mine.
Lord Hexham didn't seem to think it
would be a problem.
Nor is it, m'Lord.
Do you really want tea in the
library, m'Lady?
Apparently tea is normally served in
the ante-library here.
How interesting, Stowell. But we
will have it in the library.
~ Why must he always know better?
~ Because he always knows better.
~ Oh! It's too thrilling you could
come. ~ Welcome.
Cora!
~ How was Venice?
~ Wonderful. Sublime.
There was water all over the
streets!
~ What a marvellous place this is.
~ Do you know it?
I came here once when I was young
in old Lord Hexham's day.
~ They were trying to unload a niece.
~ The new one's not much here,
~ which is why they let out the
shooting. ~ Luckily for us!
~ Welcome to Brancaster!
~ I hope you had a decent journey.
This is Stowell, whom we brought
with us. He'll be running it all.
Quite a challenge for you.
We're not a very big party, we'll
be quite cosy.
We know some locals, which is one of
the reasons we took it.
And Lord Hexham has asked us to be
kind to his late father's pals.
That seems steep given what Lord
Sinderby must be in for.
~ Can't we use Christian names?
~ My name is not a Christian name.
~ You know what I mean.
~ Shall we go through?
Right, off you go. Quick as you can.
May I introduce myself?
I am Mr Barrow, valet to the Earl of
Grantham.
I believe you are TEMPORARY valet to
Lord Grantham.
The sad story of Mrs Bates has
reached our ears.
~ News travels fast.
~ I'm Lord Sinderby's butler, Stowell.
~ Oh, so you're a novice here, too.
~ I am not a novice anywhere.
Those are for Mr Branson.
~ He's up here without a valet.
~ Few chauffeurs travel with a valet.
Heavens, you are up-to-date with
your detail, Mr Stowell.
How can you bear to wait on him?
We do what we have to do, don't we?
On which subject, you will help out
as a footman while you're here.
~ Excuse, I am an under-butler and -
~ Lord Hexham is seldom at home,
and so they do not maintain a
full staff.
You will serve as a footman.
Don't worry, we'll find you a livery.
Are the rooms of Lady Grantham,
Lady Mary and Lady Edith close by?
~ I'm maiding all of them. ~ Then you'll
be sturdy by the time you get home.
What does Mr Branson do when the
others are shooting?
~ Pick up, or read motor magazines?
~ In fact, he's a very good shot.
Is he, indeed? I suppose that was his
training with the Fenians.
Well, I'm sorry if we're not up to
your standards, Mr Stowell.
She'll arrive about six and come
straight here.
That'll give her time to change.
~ I doubt she has much to change into.
~ Yes, well, I'll see to that.
~ And the prince?
~ I've asked him for dinner at eight.
You'll be there a few minutes before.
~ Suppose he brings his toothbrush?
~ Well, let him stay.
I mean, they're well and truly
married.
God knows I can swear to that.
And I've asked Lord Merton.
Yes, he can talk to the princess.
You know, they can discuss...
syringes and stitches and things.
Ooh, what fun you make it sound (!)
We're not a large party.
Atticus has a friend, Charlie Rogers.
He's about an hour away,
he's coming on Thursday.
And we've got the agent, Mr Pelham,
coming.
You should invite Shrimpie -
he's a marvellous shot.
I gather you've asked a few of Lord
Hexham's friends. Very good of you.
I suspect some of them have had to
overcome their principles
~ to accept my hospitality.
~ The English have strong principles
except when it comes to the chance
of good shooting or eating well.
How true!
You.
Milk.
I was wondering if I might have
some sug...
How rude!
I'm afraid Stowell's a snob.
He'll have found out about Tom's
background
~ and now he's punishing him for it.
~ Well, we can't allow that.
I don't think I've noticed that
before.
My mother's maid gave it to me as a
wedding present.
When I was a girl, if I was ill,
she would make the most delicious
chicken broth and serve it in this.
There's nothing better than chicken
broth as a pick-me-up.
No, and it really was delicious.
I remember it to this day.
She used to say,
'Every good lady's maid
should know how to make a restorative
broth.'
~ Those days are gone, I'm afraid.
~ Quite gone. Eh, Miss Denker?
I'm not sure I'd agree.
Spratt! You mustn't be jealous when
Denker is saying she can cook.
I was not so much jealous as
dubious, my lady.
You'll have to prove him wrong
one day, Denker.
Yes, prove me wrong and make us all
a delicious broth.
Well, we'll see.
That's right. Seeing is believing,
eh, Miss Denker?
I'm sorry, I thought it was settled
we'd go tomorrow.
We can if we must, but I don't see
why we're in such a hurry.
I'll be off first thing, if that's
all right, Mr Carson.
I'd love to give you something to
take for her,
~ but they wouldn't let her keep it.
~ Thank you, Mrs Hughes.
But it's knowing we're thinking of
her, that's what counts.
Poor Mr Bates. What a nightmare he
must be living through.
~ At least they let him visit a lot.
~ Only until she's convicted.
The wagons are outside.
You better get moving.
~ Oh, give anything you need to your
loader. ~ Yes.
We'll see them in the butts.
~ Absolutely.
~ So, if you'd like -
~ Rachel.
~ Yes?
~ Are you with me? ~ No, I think I'll
chum Tom for this drive.
~ Mary can keep you company.
~ As you wish.
I'm afraid your father's rather
disappointed
that I'm not inclined to welcome
your cousin Shrimpie under my roof.
Papa only said he was a good shot,
and he is.
Lord Sinderby, now that we're
family,
wouldn't it be better just to accept
the situation of Rose's parents?
Wouldn't it make it pleasanter for
everyone?
I can't pretend to approve of
divorce.
Even for you.
And you can't learn to live with it,
even for Rose's sake?
Did you shoot as a boy?
I used to shoot pigeons on my
grandfather's farm.
Pigeons - how very difficult!
Thank you.
Was it hard, joining their family?
Hard enough.
Sybil was dead, and I had to do it
on my own.
They seem much more welcoming than
we are.
I was still a shock to the system.
Daniel Sinderby is a prig.
I suppose Rachel just wants us all
to be friends.
In her husband's case, she has such
poor material to work with.
~ Robert.
~ What is it?
~ Where did you go in York?
~ Ah, here they come!
Excellent!
They haven't got a case.
Yes, you were in London, but so were
seven million other people.
You're not listening.
They've found something out.
About me.
That's nonsense. It can't be
anything that matters.
I should have told you.
And I feel badly about it now.
You know my father was a labourer.
~ He was killed in an accident at
work. ~ Yes.
When I was about six. Me, my sister
and mother were left destitute.
Until she married again, and your
stepfather was an ironworker.
~ I know all this.
~ Not all of it.
It wasn't much at first.
Slight touches.
Brushing past me.
I still remember the smell of the
beer on his breath.
Couldn't you tell your mother?
She didn't want to believe it.
What would she have done
if he'd left?
Then, one night, he kept looking at
me and I knew what was coming.
So I fetched a knife from the
scullery and I waited in the dark.
~ Are you saying you killed him?
~ No. No, of course not.
I threatened him.
And when he wouldn't stop, I...
I struck him with the blade, but I
only cut him.
~ You mean, nothing happened?
~ Well...
.. he screamed blue murder,
so the Watch came.
But my mother persuaded him
to say he slipped and fell,
that it was an accident.
After that, I took a job further up
north as a tweeny.
But it must have been in the records
and now they've found it.
Either that, or he heard I was in
prison and told them.
You're not guilty.
So there must be a way to prove it.
Do you never doubt?
I once asked you that question.
And my answer was the same as yours.
I don't doubt.
And I don't doubt that the sun
will rise in the east, either.
Thank you.
~ I wonder what the children are
doing. ~ Not worrying about us.
You're right, of course.
~ I'm sure they're being spoiled to
death. ~ Of course they are.
Might I have some bread?
Thank you, Stowell. You're very
kind.
(I do apologise.)
Poor Atticus. How can he reprimand
his father's butler?
Lord Sinderby wouldn't take kindly to
that.
The silly thing is, I don't think
Stowell likes my father-in-law.
~ He seems obsequious enough. ~ Oh, he's
all bows and deference to his face,
but my maid tells me it's a
different story behind his back.
That's a frightening thought, when
you remember what a butler knows
about the family he serves.
They know far more about us
than we do about them.
Well, it's nice, but it would take
a lot to get it up to a standard
~ where we could charge money
to stay there. ~ Oh, not so much.
We'd employ the estate workers
and I'd supervise.
While I'd be supervising the mythical
'maid of all work'.
We'd SHARE the duties.
That's the whole point.
All right. Where's the next one?
We take the bus to Helmsley
and then it's a bit of a hike.
Keep calm. I'm not dead yet!
It was kind of you to send
a motor car.
We didn't want you to get lost.
~ Where is the princess?
~ She's upstairs changing.
We haven't seen her yet, any of us.
I borrow this from the Theatre
Royale.
Oh!
Well, shall we...?
Are you sure you wouldn't rather
greet her in a room by yourself?
~ We can always scoot back.
~ No, no.
It will be easier not to be alone
at first.
I haven't seen her for five years.
I want you all here.
The presence of strangers is our only
guarantee of good behaviour.
I hate the way Stowell treats
Mr Branson.
He isn't polite downstairs.
He doesn't approve of Mr Branson's
bettering himself.
What right has he to approve
or disapprove?
Anyway, Lady Rose says he doesn't
even like Lord Sinderby.
~ I'm not sure His Lordship's very
easy to like. ~ True enough.
But is there any way to get Stowell
a black mark?
~ Can't Barrow come up with something?
~ Er...
You're right, Mr Barrow usually has
a card or two up his sleeve.
Well, tell him to get one out of his
sleeve and play it. Pronto.
~ I don't mind taking him down a peg
or two. ~ But how?
Mm.
Let me think about it
while I'm cleaning these.
~ That reminds me - have you seen Lord
Sinderby's valet? ~ Why?
Ran out of waterproofing wax.
Excuse me. Do you know where I can
find Lord Sinderby's valet?
~ Mr Daunt? He's gone out. He won't be
back before ten. ~ Thank you.
I think I've got an idea.
Do you think Lard Mary would mind
annoying Lord Sinderby?
~ None of our lot would mind.
~ Will you help me?
I suppose so, seeing as it's what
Lady Mary's asked for.
~ Then there's your answer.
~ I don't understand.
You will. We need a piece of paper
and a pencil.
Come with me.
The Princess Kuragin.
~ Igor.
~ Irina.
Shall I introduce everyone?
If you wish. But what difference
will it make?
~ Uh... Y-You've had a long journey,
Princess. ~ Obviously.
I would so like to go to Russia.
I'm afraid I never have.
Then you've missed it.
~ Do you have everything you need?
~ I wear the clothes you had put out.
~ I didn't know if you'd have your
luggage with you. ~ I have no luggage.
~ I have no possessions to put in my
luggage. ~ Come, my dear.
Nothing is more tedious than other
people's misfortunes.
~ Let us just be grateful
to Lady Grantham. ~ Hm!
Last time we met, the circumstances
were rather different.
~ I don't remember.
~ I think you do.
Ah! There's a note here for
a Mrs Brennan. Who's that?
~ The cook. Why? ~ As I say,
somebody's left a note for her.
So you better take it in.
How can you be sure they won't trace
it back to us?
I'm not a complete amateur, Miss
Baxter. Give me some credit.
It's rather a nuisance, but Charlie
Rogers has rung to say
he's got a friend staying, so he's
got to bring him or chuck.
~ What will you do? ~ I've said to bring
him, but it means I can't shoot.
~ How infuriating. Who is he?
~ He's called Henry Talbot.
~ I don't know anything about him.
~ I'll tell the agent not to come.
Oh, no. Poor Mr Pelham, that's too
unkind.
~ I don't know why, but we all feel
a bit sorry for him. ~ Oh.
Oh, this is very nice, Mrs Patmore.
Quite a treat.
Well, the cat's away, so we mice
might as well play a little.
~ Who have you invited?
~ Oh, just us,
Mr Bates, Mr Molesley and Daisy.
Daisy? To wait on us, I assume?
To wait on us and eat with us.
If that thought's too democratically
overpowering,
you can share what I've made for the
housemaids.
It is your choice.
~ Is everything settled?
~ What's this?
Mr Murray's coming tomorrow to see
Anna
and he's got permission for Mr Bates
to be present.
I'll be gone most of the day. I hope
to speak to him afterwards.
Of course. Don't worry.
We'll expect you when we see you.
Here's Mr Molesley.
Now we can begin.
Hope I haven't kept you waiting!
I wonder whether I might have some
wine?
You've not had any? Stowell, what's
the matter with you?
What the devil's going on?
Rachel, can you explain this?
~ Explain what? ~ Why am I not being
given anything decent to eat?
I don't know. Stowell?
~ It was Your Lordship's order.
~ What are you talking about?
~ What is the matter with you tonight?
~ Mr Daunt left a note for the cook,
~ saying you'd asked -
~ I never said a thing to Daunt!
And why are you so rude
to Mr Branson?
~ There's no need - ~ The cook
told me you requested simple -
Stowell,
someone's played a joke on us.
Now, when you got the note, did it
look like Daunt's writing?
I never saw the note.
~ And obviously Mrs Brennan is not
familiar - ~ What?!
Do you dare to use the word
'obviously' when you contradict me?
Now take this away,
fetch me some dinner
and conduct yourself more
professionally in the future.
And bring that back, you stupid fool!
We're not shooting tomorrow, so
would you like to see the estate?
What fun that would be. Don't you
think so, Robert?
~ Goodness.
~ He does get so rattled by things.
I'm not very keen on your butler, so
I'm afraid I rather enjoyed it.
Well, maybe, but Stowell's a proud
chap.
He won't find that easy to forgive.
I don't think Barrow will much like
being called a stupid fool.
I think you'll enjoy Paris.
Oh, many of our countrymen have
settled there.
Of course, they've lost everything,
but so have we.
Including the will to live.
Well, if you're going to be
miserable,
you might as well do it in charming
surroundings.
With your permission,
I am going up now.
I hope you will be comfortable.
My maid, Denker, will be looking
after you.
I will be more comfortable tonight
than I will ever be again.
You don't know that.
But I do, Mrs Crawley.
Goodnight.
What time will you call for the
princess in the morning?
Whenever suits you. If that's what
you've decided.
Me?
I'm surprised you think there is
still a decision to be made.
You are good to lend her those
things.
They're given, not lent.
So...
.. tomorrow we say goodbye.
Is that what you really want?
It's how it must be.
~ I don't understand you.
~ You will, if you try.
~ Spratt will see you to the car.
~ I'll do that.
~ I should be going.
~ Oh, thank you.
Good night.
I have the sense that a game of high
stakes has been played here tonight.
Although I couldn't tell you
who the winner is.
Me, I hope.
Good night.
So, have you told the prince his
cause is hopeless?
Yes.
I am sad to say.
Sad?
I will never again receive
an immoral proposition from a man.
Was I so wrong to savour it?
Ow.
What is the matter?
I should go. Barrow will be waiting
for me in the dressing room.
Let him wait! I want you tell me
whatever it is you're hiding.
I'm not hiding it, exactly.
It's probably nothing.
And what if it isn't nothing?
I've been having some pains
in my chest.
~ Well, my chest, my side, my tummy.
~ What sort of pains?
Quite sharp.
So I went to see a man I'd heard
about in York.
~ He said I have - well, I might have
angina. ~ Oh, my God!
This is why I didn't want to tell
you about it.
It doesn't mean that I'm about to
drop down dead of a heart attack.
But he wants me to go for tests when
we get back.
~ Then you shouldn't be shooting.
~ He said if it relaxes me, it's fine.
I don't know how relaxing this trip
is.
It was unpleasant, wasn't it, to see
a man shouting at his butler.
~ I think I will speak to Edith.
~ Why now?
Well,
you never know what's coming, do
you?
I want to make it clear that
everything's all right between us.
Please look after yourself!
But that's your job, my darling, and
you do it so well.
Mrs Crawley said how much she
enjoyed the evening, m'Lady.
It was colourful. Thank Mrs Potter
for the delicious dinner,
but please tell her I need a rest
from such rich delights.
~ Are you ready to go up, m'Lady?
~ Yes.
What about some of Miss Denker's
famous broth?
I'm aware that you're teasing,
Spratt,
but as a matter of fact, it would be
very nice.
Miss Denker, would you take up the
challenge of the wooden spoon?
Wouldn't I be in Mrs Potter's way?
I'd never want to be a nuisance.
I bet you wouldn't. There's a stove
in the still room.
~ Could you manage with that, Denker?
~ I'd be delighted, m'Lady.
You see, Spratt, not every spring and
lever evades your touch.
Come in.
~ Papa, is something the matter?
~ No, nothing's the matter.
~ And that's what I want to make
clear. ~ I don't understand.
What's this about?
Marigold.
I see.
And what do you want to say about
Marigold?
I think you know what I want to say,
what I want you to say.
I can't give her up.
Of course not.
Have you told Tom?
No.
~ But he might have guessed.
~ So now everyone knows?
Everyone except Mary.
I want your forgiveness, Papa.
Am I allowed to say that, still?
It's not the way I'd have had
things,
I won't lie to you about that,
but this is what's happened.
~ I believe Michael Gregson was an
honourable man. ~ Oh, he was, Papa.
He really was.
He would have married me as soon as
he could, I know that.
I think so, too.
So now we must do our best
for his child,
for his sake, as well as yours.
That's so lovely of you.
But I think we should keep it
in the family.
Even in 1924, there are plenty of
people who might be unpleasant.
But...
do you forgive me, Papa?
Oh, my darling, I'm sure I need your
forgiveness
quite as much as you need mine.
Now, go to bed.
And sleep well.
I gather you got more than you
bargained for.
I've had my run-ins
with His Lordship before,
but I have never been insulted in
public, and I don't intend to start
now.
Still, Mr Stowell got a flea in his
ear and that's what we wanted.
What you and Lady Mary wanted,
perhaps. I've got bigger plans now.
~ What do you mean?
~ Oh, you'll see.
Yes.
What do you want?
To add my sympathy, Mr Stowell.
He insulted me an' all, you know.
I felt for you, and I thought
you showed great restraint.
For a servant in that situation,
restraint is Hobson's choice.
Write something.
~ How do you mean?
~ Write something.
'My name is Barrow and I live in
Yorkshire.'
~ It wasn't you, then.
~ Why would it be me?
The staff resent me.
Their butler's on holiday and they
hate taking orders from me.
That doesn't give his His Lordship
much excuse to behave as he did.
'His Lordship'!
His Lordship, with a title that's
not ten minutes old.
I know a lot about His
Dirty-fingered Lordship.
~ And he's forgotten that.
~ I expect you could tell me things
you wouldn't much like to read
on the front page of The Times.
You'd be surprised.
Go on, then... surprise me.
It's a shame Lord Sinderby wouldn't
come.
Mother did ask him. She thought it
might get rid of
some of the nasty taste of last
night, but he said, 'No.'
He's a difficult man. O-Or shouldn't
I say that?
You can say what you like after that
dinner.
Oh, well, at least we gave the
county something to talk about.
I wonder what the truth was about the
letter from the valet.
Baxter says it was one of the castle
staff. They hate Stowell.
~ They'll hear no argument from me.
~ Well, it's over now.
Why were you all in a huddle at
breakfast?
Atticus has been offered a job in New
York.
Oh, congratulations.
Thank you. Aren't you going to
America soon?
~ I-I am. I'm going to Boston.
~ When?
I'm planning to spend Christmas at
Downton and leave in the new year.
~ Well, it hasn't been decided yet.
~ Poor Mary.
She hates to be left behind
when everyone else is getting on
with their lives.
This isn't that - it's the thought
of being left with you.
You can't manage a broth, Miss
Denker, special or otherwise?
~ I'd be very good at it.
~ If you only knew where to start.
I should never have volunteered.
But if you'd seen the look
on Mr Spratt's face,
you'd have sworn you could paint the
Mona Lisa and be finished by teatime.
~ Won't Mrs Potter help?
~ I don't trust her.
~ I think she's in league with the
enemy. ~ Blimey!
We'd all better come work at the
Dower House.
Sounds more exciting than here.
How much attention will they pay to
Mrs Bates' past?
Well, you can see the problem -
a man attacks her, she stabs him
with a knife.
Now there's another attack and she
pushes him to his death
on a busy road.
There is... a pattern.
If that's what you think, then why
are you here?
Mrs Bates, I hope we've not left our
manners outside the prison gates.
Of course, your stepfather didn't
bring a charge against you.
That was my mother's doing.
It may mean we can have it ruled as
inadmissible.
That would undermine their case and
it might never come to a trial.
~ Can you achieve such a ruling?
~ I will do everything I can.
You seem to think I'm angry with
your sons. I'm not at all!
Then why can't we forget that
horrible evening happened?
I'm not angry with them,
but I accept they have no desire to
see their mother replaced.
This is my fault. I've taken such
care to shield them from the truth.
~ Which is?
~ I was wretched with their mother.
~ Perhaps she was wretched with you.
~ No doubt. We were very ill-suited.
But now they're preventing my first
chance of real happiness.
I'm sorry, but I'm not prepared to
live the rest of my life
in an atmosphere of loathing and
resentment.
I will not come between
a father and his sons.
Then may I ask you to be honest?
Is that the only barrier?
If they were to welcome you into
the family, you would marry me?
I would.
And I should be very glad to.
So,
there is my challenge.
How do you get rid of all this scum?
It's the onions - they're only
supposed to sweat,
but I think they fell down
exhausted.
And you went a bit mad with the
salt.
Shall we taste it?
Oh, my God!
Why don't I just make a bottle of
it?
Then I could bring it to the house,
you could warm it through
and serve it. No-one will ever know.
For now, we could give you all the
ingredients
so you could chop them about
for Mr Spratt's benefit.
I'll use every precedent there is.
But if the story's admitted as
evidence, will she be convicted?
Where the law is concerned, you can
never be sure about anything.
Will she?
They have a strong motive, and they
can prove opportunity
~ because she was in London, which we
do not deny. ~ No.
Now she's been identified on the
pavement nearby at that moment.
They'll use the earlier case to prove
it wasn't against her nature.
It's quite strong, I'm afraid.
The cook's happy for you to announce
dinner.
Thank you.
Mr Barrow.
I'm afraid I said too much last
night.
I was angry, and I'd had more to
drink than was good for me.
Don't worry about that, Mr Stowell,
I've got a mind like a sieve.
That's dinner, everyone.
Will you shoot tomorrow, or have you
given way to the uninvited guest?
~ I don't think I have a choice.
~ You can have my place.
Certainly not! I've had two good
days, we're out on Friday,
~ so I don't merit pity.
~ I hope your neighbour knows
~ how accommodating you're being.
~ You can tell him -
~ he's staying the night.
~ Don't tempt me.
I do find it astonishing the way
people take these things for granted.
We can't all be as unselfish as you,
Mary. Just joking!
You'll like this.
It's not dear, but I think
it's very good value.
I've done the sums
and I believe
we should put an offer in
on the house on Brancour Road.
~ Before I agree to be part of it?
~ I hope you will agree.
To our future as property magnates.
Very well.
I can see there's no escape, and I
must tell the truth.
~ I've never caught you in a lie.
~ No, I don't lie,
but there are things I don't say.
I've allowed this folly to go on
because... I don't know, really,
because it was a nice idea.
And I would have liked to come in
with you, I would have...
~ But you won't.
~ I won't, because I can't.
I don't know if I've ever told you
that I have a sister.
I've always thought you had no
family left.
Which may be because that's what I
wanted you to think.
My sister Becky was born...
She's not quite right in the head.
While my mother was alive, she
looked after her,
~ but when she died...
~ There was no-one but you.
Precisely.
My choice was simple.
Either I gave up work and we lived on
a pittance,
or I went on working and paid for her
to be cared for.
But that must have cost a fortune.
It cost every penny I could spare.
So there you have it, I've got no
savings because I've got no money.
I'm a pauper.
But... what about your retirement?
~ Have you not paid into any schemes?
~ I can't retire.
I must work for as long as anyone
will let me.
I wish you very well with your house,
Mr Cason - you've earned it.
But there is no place for me
in the project.
~ Now I've embarrassed you.
~ Mm.
I'm not embarrassed.
I'm ashamed
that I've chivvied and bullied you,
when if I'd had any sensitivity at
all -
No, don't say that.
I've enjoyed our little dream.
~ I'm the one to blame for stringing
you along. ~ Oh, never.
Well, as I say, I hope you buy it.
~ I hope you're able to without me.
~ I am, but...
I've had a telegram from Mr Murray.
May I use your telephone, Mr Carson?
He says it's bad news.
Oh, no. I'm sorry to hear that.
Be my guest.
Rose, you chum Tom.
Mary, go with Mr Talbot.
Rachel...
~ Oh, sort it out between you.
~ I'll see you all there.
~ I'm not sure where I'm supposed to
go. ~ He's such a controller.
Go where you'd like. Mr Rogers?
~ Would it be awful if I were left
alone with my loader? ~ Of course not.
I wouldn't mind, if you've nothing
better to do.
I'm Bertie Pelham, the agent.
~ Are you often asked to come when
there's shooting? ~ No, I'm not.
I'm staying for dinner, which they
REALLY didn't have to do.
It's very kind.
Thanks for keeping my spirits up.
Some men hate having strangers with
them. My father does.
Oh, I don't mind. Especially not you.
You're staying with Mr Rogers,
aren't you?
That's right. Lord Sinderby said he
could bring me.
~ Very decent of him.
~ Do you shoot at lot?
Not at this level.
That explains it.
~ What explains what?
~ Nothing.
~ No, go on, I insist.
~ Well, it's none of my business,
but Atticus isn't shooting to make
room for you.
Lord Sinderby's son? That's terrible.
Why didn't somebody tell Charlie
there was no room?
They thought it inhospitable.
As soon as this drive's over,
I'll swap places.
No, don't. His guns are back at
the castle, it's all settled now.
Look, forget I said anything.
Is your husband one of the other
guns?
No, although my late husband was
quite good at it.
In the end.
You're a young widow.
But then I suppose the war gave us
many young widows.
It wasn't the war. In fact...
Look out. Here they come.
~ Well done!
~ Fluke.
~ How long have you been the agent?
~ About a year and a half.
~ But I've known Brancaster all my
life. ~ Oh?
The old Lord Hexham was my father's
cousin.
Second cousin.
They've both dead now, but we used
to come here every so often.
Which is why you were given the job?
~ That's rather a leading question.
~ Sorry!
Of course, you're right.
When my father died, I left the
Army.
I didn't know what to do next,
and I suppose Cousin Peter felt
sorry for me.
~ No burning ambitions?
~ Not really.
I'm always jealous of those chaps
who fly the Channel, invent a cure
or something.
What about you? Are you pining for
some unfulfilled dream?
Not today.
Today I feel... very happy.
Good morning, Daisy.
Can I help you with anything?
No, thank you, Mr Spratt.
I were just...
I looked in on Miss Denker.
I see.
What are you carrying so diligently?
Ah!
~ Basket's empty.
~ Yes.
~ I'm looking in at the shops on my
way back. ~ Ah.
I have news of my own.
As you know, I told you I'd
discussed it all with Dickie.
You agreed to marry him if he could
bring his sons around.
This morning... I had a letter
from Larry Grey.
Oh, goodness! Is it polite?
Judge for yourself.
'Dear Mrs Crawley.'
Well, that's a good start.
The sentiment of the greeting is not
reflected in the text.
'My father has requested that I
re-examine my feelings
when it comes to your proposed
union.
I have re-examined them and I find
them to be unchanged.
I hope you'll persuade him to avoid
any further attempts
to make me reconsider,
which could only prove embarrassing
to us both.'
'Yours sincerely, Larry Grey.'
~ Have you shown this to him?
~ Not yet.
I'm not sure I should.
And I suppose you'll take it lying
down.
I'll take it lying down, standing up
or in a semi-recumbent posture.
The matter is decided.
I will not have my final years
overshadowed
by a tear-stained tug of war.
I suppose there's one consolation.
What's that?
Dr Clarkson will be delighted!
Thank you.
What's that?
Murray telephoned this morning.
There's a date for Anna's trial.
~ Oh, no.
~ What's that?
Anna's going for tr-
That settles it. You will not shoot
any more today, or tomorrow.
~ Don't embarrass me, please.
~ I won't if you do as I say.
What can I do to help?
Take my place this afternoon.
~ What's the matter, Papa?
~ I'm perfectly all right,
I just need to take things a little
easy.
If only he'd chosen not to be all
man-like and keep it concealed.
Is there anything I can do?
You could send someone to fetch Mr
Aldridge's guns.
You see, this is why I didn't want
to make a thing of it.
~ Is it really true about Anna?
~ We'll know more when we get home.
You've probably heard
you're off the hook.
Papa's given his place to Atticus,
so you'll pay no price for your
thoughtlessness.
Be a sport and forgive me.
I'm here for the night, I don't want
you scowling at me through dinner.
~ I shall scowl if I think you deserve
it. ~ I never meant it to happen.
Isn't there something called
'forgiveness through good intention'?
Only for Catholics. Let's sit down.
Surely you can't have meant for
Daisy to make the broth
instead of your good self?
This is all for show, isn't it?
Your intention was to serve Daisy's
excellent soup
and take the credit yourself.
What have you done with it?
I felt it would be discourteous to
give it back,
so it just seems best to pour it
away and never speak of it again.
Don't you agree? You must make it
yourself now, Miss Denker.
Good luck to you.
~ I'm glad to find you here and not in
bed. Have you recovered? ~ Completely.
~ I suppose I missed a marvellous
afternoon. ~ Spectacular.
~ Is Papa really ill?
~ I don't know.
Now I just want to get him home in
one piece.
I think we should wait a few
minutes.
Stowell, who is this?
~ God Almighty.
~ What is it? What's happened?
What the hell is she doing here?
~ What's her name? Tell me her name.
~ What?
Tell me her name and I'll save you.
Diana.
Diana Clark.
Diana. I don't believe you.
I never thought you'd make it!
~ This is my friend, Diana Clark.
~ Oh!
She said she'd be in the
neighbourhood
and I asked her to look in if she
had any time.
You must stay for tea. And what is
this little chap called?
Er... Dan-Daniel.
Daniel? How extraordinary -
that's Lord Sinderby's name.
Would you come with me? Come on.
Play along and it will be fine.
The telegram said he'd be alone and
to bring the boy.
I'm sure it did, but unfortunately
he didn't send it.
Hello. I'm Atticus, Rose's husband.
Why have we never met before?
I agree. How silly is that?
Who is that woman? She can't be a
great friend of Rose,
~ I've never seen her before in my
life. ~ Nor me.
The truth is, I asked Barrow to get
Stowell into trouble,
and I'm afraid he overdid it.
What's the matter?
You look as if you've had a stroke.
Oh, I can't have two of you laid up
in one day.
Just a bit tired, that's all.
~ I'll lie down before dinner.
~ All right.
We're so interested to meet your very
old friend Mrs Clark,
~ whom we have never clapped eyes on
before. ~ (Help me.)
~ Only if you tell me what's going on.
~ (Come.)
Oh, of course, you all know each
other.
Diana, it's so lovely to see you
again.
Indeed it is.
How have you been since you were
last at Downton?
~ Oh... well. Awfully, awfully well.
~ Will you excuse me?
I wish he'd come and speak to me. I
suppose he can't.
Who?
Oh, crikey! No, he can't.
I've come all the way from London.
Who would do such a nasty thing?
Oh, I think I know, and I think I
know why.
But it won't help to tell you.
~ Mr Bates! Are you going somewhere?
~ I am.
In fact, can I ask a favour,
Mr Molesley?
Can you give these to Mr Carson?
~ He'll know what to do with him.
~ He's about somewhere.
I'd rather not see him. And don't
give them to him yet.
~ Wait till this evening.
~ Mr Bates, are you in trouble?
My wife's in prison - I'd call that
trouble, wouldn't you?
Because I want you to know I'd
gladly help you in any way I can.
I'm touched by that. I mean it.
Thank you.
But the only way you can help me now
is by delivering those letters.
Just a moment.
You acted to save Lord Sinderby, but
you saved me, too.
~ From a hideous situation,
and I am so grateful. ~ No need.
~ Please try not to think ill of him.
~ Oh, I'm not sure what I think.
Maybe it's good to know he has the
same feet of clay as the rest of us.
~ Goodbye, Mrs Clark.
~ Oh, you must call her Diana.
~ Diana. No doubt we'll meet in London.
I look forward to it. ~ Me, too.
Are you off?
No, I'm just going up to change, but
I can't find my white tie.
~ Of course! I forgot you were staying
for dinner. ~ Oh!
Stowell looks like he's in a cage
with a tiger.
Are you going to give him away to
your father-in-law?
Stowell!
How did you know about Mrs Clark?
Will you tell His Lordship, m'Lady?
I can't decide.
But... in the meantime, I hope you
can be more polite to Mr Branson
~ while he's with us.
~ Certainly, m'Lady.
Rose, Mary, Robert.
Would you stay in here for a moment,
please?
I'm glad to have caught you three.
~ I wasn't sure I could manage it.
~ I'm intrigued.
Oh, you needn't pretend.
You saw the depths of my humiliation
earlier.
Who planned it, I wonder?
Everyone has enemies.
I'd be grateful if we could restrict
this knowledge to our number.
I do not believe any of you would
wish to cause Rachel or Atticus pain.
No-one else will ever know.
The truth is, it could all have been
very much worse.
And that it was not
is due entirely to Rose.
Rose, my dear...
.. you are clever, kind
and resourceful.
And I wish to put it on record
that I see now that we are lucky to
have you in the family.
I shall be inviting your parents to
stay as soon as is convenient.
~ You don't have to.
~ Oh, I think I do.
We all know that people who live in
glass houses
are ill-advised to throw stones.
Now, I've had a gramophone put into
the library,
~ so run along and enjoy yourselves.
~ Golly! What fun!
Thank you.
She'll love you forever
if you'll let her.
That's who she is.
I know that now.
I was stupid not to have seen it
before.
The letters to His Lordship and
Mr Murray must tell the same story.
Why confess? It makes no sense.
The police said someone short pushed
Mr Green.
Mr Bates isn't short!
Didn't he spend that day in York?
~ The lost ticket was never used.
~ If only it wasn't lost.
Do we know what he was doing there?
He said he had lunch in a pub, he
couldn't remember which one.
There are hundreds of pubs in York.
But Mr Bates had lunch in one of
them.
I don't believe he's guilty, whatever
he's written there.
He just wants Anna out of prison, and
I don't blame him for that.
Might I have the key for Mr Bates'
cottage?
You never know, he might have left
a clue as to where he was going.
I'm not sure what we'll do with it
if he has, but you can have the key.
(Is there anything I can get you,
sir? Anything you'd like?)
N-No. No, thank you, Stowell.
You've been very considerate.
~ That makes it all worth it.
~ Makes what worth it?
It would take too long to explain.
Suffice to say, the butler is back in
his box.
~ Well, that sounds rather snobbish.
~ Not in this instance.
What was really going on this
afternoon with that woman?
The one with the little boy in tow.
What makes you think there was
anything going on?
All right. Why was Lord Sinderby
in a panic?
Why did Lady Rose take over?
Why did your father pretend to know
the visitor when he clearly did not?
And why was Lady Sinderby in total
ignorance throughout?
Naturally, I'm not going to answer
any of your questions,
but I'm impressed you should ask
them. Well done.
~ Are you looking forward to going
home? ~ Why, particularly?
~ Aren't you missing Marigold?
~ Aren't you missing Sybbie?
Isn't Mary missing George?
Not quite as much.
What are you trying to say?
Not a lot, really.
But these will be my last months at
Downton,
and you have always been my ally.
I'd like to feel we were honest with
each other.
You see, where I grew up, there were
quite a few Marigolds.
~ I'm not sure I understand you.
~ I think you do.
My cousin Nuala had a child that was
brought up as her sister.
No-one talked of it, naturally, but
we all knew.
~ I told Papa you'd guessed.
~ So they're both in on it?
They are now.
~ And Mary? Does she know?
~ No.
She's completely uninterested in me,
which should keep me safe.
Please, keep it to yourself.
Not for my sake so much as for hers.
You may not believe it, but I'm a
signed-up member of this family now.
~ Can I have this one?
~ Of course.
You look very intense.
Oh, we were just talking about our
ward.
My family adopted a little girl.
She's growing up at Downton.
What's the new Lord Hexham like?
He must be your cousin.
My third cousin. Does that count?
Is he nice?
Peter's all right.
He's not here much.
Always seems to be in North Africa.
Do you always ask so many questions?
I'm glad I've caught you.
They said in the dining room
you'd left.
~ I hope it didn't spoil your
breakfast. ~ I haven't had it yet.
We wanted to make an early start.
~ Charlie's got something on this
afternoon. ~ Well, goodbye, Mr Talbot.
I feel guilty now trying to make you
feel uncomfortable yesterday.
But you were quite right.
I'll be less... cavalier next time.
Maybe we'll meet again.
Are you ever in Yorkshire?
I have an aunt up there. So you
never know.
~ Perhaps we'll meet shooting.
~ Maybe.
~ But it's not my real sport.
~ What is?
Cars.
~ Cars?
~ Henry, we must go.
Heavens! What a snappy chariot.
Mr Rogers clearly has hidden depths.
It's mine.
But thanks for the compliment.
~ Welcome back, my Lord.
~ Carson.
There's been a development while you
were away.
Mr Bates has gone.
~ I don't understand. Gone where?
~ We don't know, my Lord,
~ but he's left you a letter.
~ How very mysterious.
Come on.
Mr Carson. So, does that mean I stay
on as valet,
~ or am I expected to double up?
~ It all has to be thought through.
They must release Mrs Bates
now that they've got a confession.
No doubt His Lordship is telephoning
Mr Murray as we speak.
~ Will he be hiding somewhere?
~ In Ireland, I presume.
He has family there. And the English
police are not too well regarded
if they try to find him.
Why hasn't Anna been released?
Why did Carson wait?
I'll telephone Murray now. He'll be
able to get her out.
~ I don't believe for a moment Bates
did it. ~ No!
But neither did Anna. So it won't be
unjust to set her free.
Have you caught up with yourself?
I'll be straight by the time
they finish dinner.
Mr Molesley,
when you said earlier about what
you were planning to for Mr Bates,
~ using his photo...
~ Yes?
I'd like to be helpful.
I'd like to...
~ .. come with you.
~ Would you?
Because that would help a lot!
But I don't want anyone else to
know.
Not unless it works.
He's sure he can get her out at
once. He's coming up tomorrow.
~ Well, that's something.
~ Yes.
What is it?
In his letter to me,
Bates has left instructions
for how to get a message through
to him.
~ An Irish address and telephone
number. ~ Has he told anyone else?
Not as far I as know. Not Carson.
What do you think I should do?
What you should do is easy -
tell the police.
But what I would do is keep it secret
until we know more.
Thank heaven we both have a criminal
turn of mind.
~ I should go in round the back.
~ No, no, no.
Come this way to say hello to
His Lordship.
~ I saw the car. What a relief.
~ We were waiting for it.
Yes, but I'm not released, m'Lord.
~ I'm still on bail.
~ Maybe.
But with a signed confession and a
man on the run,
they could never hope for a guilty
verdict.
And if they find him and prove him
innocent, do I go back to prison?
It is a very frustrating situation.
If he's guilty, I'm innocent.
And if I'm guilty, he's innocent.
~ Except neither of us did it.
~ Which is what we must prove.
You're home now, that's something.
At least we're going forwards, not
backwards.
Now, can the car take me to the
station?
Stark will drive us both. I have to
be in York in half an hour,
so I'm leaving now.
~ Carson, will you tell Her Ladyship
where I've gone? ~ Certainly, my Lord.
Do you want to come in this way?
No, I'll go round by the kitchen
courtyard, m'Lady.
Might as well get back into the
swing of things.
Well, so this is the famous broth?
What else would it be?
Are you ready to be judged on it?
I shall be judged by you, Mr Spratt,
whatever happens.
If you mean I will judge you for
promoting yourself
through lies and fraud,
then, yes, I will.
So will she.
Your unmasking is at hand.
God in Heaven!
Oh, Denker.
~ Oh.
~ I was talking menus with Mrs Potter,
and Spratt reminded me about the
broth.
~ He didn't want your efforts to be
overlooked. ~ I'm sure he didn't.
Not a chance!
~ Of course, the proof of the pudding
is in he eating, m'Lady. ~ Indeed.
So, may I taste it?
Uh...
Thank you.
I warned you, m'Lady.
It is...
delicious.
It can't be! It's not possible!
There's a point, Spratt, where malice
ceases to be amusing.
Thank you, Denker, very much.
I'm not hungry enough to do your soup
justice this evening.
Let us... save its delights for
another day.
Whatever you wish, Your Ladyship.
~ Thank you.
~ Thank you. Thank you.
I thought you'd look in before you
came down.
~ To tell you how I got on in York?
~ Yes.
I wanted to wait until we were all
together.
You'll be pleased to hear I am not
about to have a heart attack.
~ Your father has an ulcer.
~ Oh, that's a relief!
Yes, it is a relief, but you've got
to be good with your diet.
Well said. We'll take it seriously -
white fish, chicken, no alcohol.
~ Steady on!
~ I mean it! You frightened me.
~ I don't like to be frightened.
~ There must be room for negotiation.
Why don't you promise to lay off
everything until Christmas Day?
~ Christmas Eve.
~ Very well. Christmas Eve. Mama?
I suppose. But I'll be strict.
We'll have a merry Christmas as
my last memory of Downton.
~ Don't make it sound so final!
~ I'll be back one day.
~ I'll need to see how the village
turned out. ~ That reminds me.
Good news in the Evening Post. The
Della Francesca sold amazingly well.
~ That's wonderful.
~ Let's go through.
Shall we?
Wonderful news. Congratulations.
Hallelujah. We are to have another
footman to help you, Mr Molesley.
How did you wangle that?
His Lordship has had some good news,
I shamelessly took advantage.
Did I hear right?
Are we to have a new footman?
Do your ears have wireless aerials?
I hope you'll give another chance to
Andy.
~ The lad we had in London for Lady
Rose's wedding? ~ He was nice.
I remember him gabbing around town
with Miss Denker
~ and staying out till all hours.
~ I had no trouble with the lad.
But it's your decision.
Are you ready for the lights?
Three, two, one...
It's beautiful, Daddy!
No luck there.
Shall we have a break after the next
one?
~ I think that's a good idea.
~ Where to now?
I believe it's the Fountain Inn.
Shut your eyes!
I...thought you'd like to know
I've bought the house.
~ We've completed.
~ Oh, I am pleased.
That's a nice thing to know before
Christmas.
You can open them now.
Oh!
Will we be a big party?
Family, really.
Mr Atticus and Lady Rose are coming,
which is nice.
His parents won't bother with
Christmas.
Don't start!
Then I gather they're off to
New York in January,
~ when Mr Branson goes to Boston.
~ Yeah.
I'll miss him.
I don't mind admitting it.
I know you're uncomfortable with him,
but I feel he's a sort of bridge
between us all.
~ I'm... used to him. I'll say that.
~ Heavens!
Don't let him hear you, it'll go
straight to his head.
Ah, Mr Carson. Might I trouble you
for a moment, please?
Come in. I understand you asked to
see me. Carson will stay.
~ It's about Mr Bates, my Lord.
~ So Carson tells us.
Please, we're all anxious to hear
anything to Bates' good.
How can we get a message to him?
That's what worries me.
Let us concern ourselves with that
when we know the new evidence.
Mrs Bates told the police he'd spent
the day Mr Green died
walking round York.
He said he'd eaten in a pub,
but he couldn't identify it.
~ He must have been out of his mind.
Is it any wonder he'd forgotten? ~ No.
But we know which pub it was.
What?!
I took a photograph of Mr Bates,
and Miss Baxter and I,
we've spent our days off
walking around the city,
~ and questioning the landlords.
~ But it must have taken forever.
~ How long have you been doing this?
~ Since we came back from Brancaster.
~ How many pubs have you visited?
~ 60, 70.
We had a list of them and we ticked
them off one by one.
We had a third to do when we found
it.
It's er...
~ a Mr Salter of the Picarol in King
Street. ~ He'll swear to this?
He will, m'Lady.
He remembered Mr Bates' limp.
And he also remembered how he almost
got angry
~ when Mr Salter tried to help him to
a table. ~ Sounds like Bates.
Then they started talking
and it turned out they'd both served
in the South African war.
Mr Bates is quite distinctive, so I
believed we had a good chance.
May I make a suggestion?
If Mr Viner accepts this man's
statement,
surely it would overturn any attempt
to prosecute?
If this does prove Bates' innocence,
which clearly it does,
won't they re-arrest Anna?
We'll cross that bridge when we
come to it.
~ We can't leave Bates on the run when
he's innocent. ~ Of course not.
Molesley, Baxter, you've done
something fine.
Generous and fine.
I'll telephone Mr Murray at once,
but I'm sure neither Bates, nor we,
~ can adequately express our
gratitude. ~ Thank you, m'Lord.
I've spoken to Murray.
He's certain there won't be a
problem once he has the statement.
~ Have you sent a message to Bates?
~ I can't decide.
Tell him to come. When he's arrived,
contact Murray
~ without saying where he is.
~ Poor old Murray.
We'll have him running a thieves'
kitchen before we're finished.
~ Do you think they'll re-arrest Anna?
~ Murray says not.
The witness who identified her is
having doubts.
The police know their case would be
shredded in court.
Something else may turn up, but
until it does...
They'll leave her at liberty. Well,
thank heaven.
I can't stop thinking about Tom
leaving.
I suppose there's no point in trying
to persuade him
~ to let Sybbie stay.
~ No point at all.
How are you feeling?
Oh, better.
Much better. Bored to sobs, but
better.
Please be careful on Christmas Eve if
you do decide to drink.
~ You'll get plastered on a sniff of
sherry. ~ Paradise.
I'm serious.
You can't make a fool of yourself in
front of the tenants.
They'd be uncomfortable.
I'm glad the picture sold so well, it
makes me feel better
about spoiling it for you.
There is not now, nor ever will be,
anything you have spoiled for me.
Well, don't spoil Christmas Eve for
me.
Oh, my.
Taste that, Mrs Hughes.
Maybe you'll write a cookery book,
Daisy.
Maybe that's where she's headed.
Oh, I hope you change your mind
about your studies.
Start the new year with a new
determination.
I can't bear for it to go to waste.
You're always complaining they keep
me from my work!
~ You know I don't mean it!
~ Anything could happen for you.
~ It's a wonderful feeling.
~ Maybe.
If it means a bit of extra work for
me, so be it!
And happy Christmas!
Why didn't you show it to me before
this? It's been months!
Well, I've shown you now.
You must know I resent Larry's
treatment of you very much.
~ Things can never be good between us
again. ~ It will not involve me.
~ Nothing will make you change
your mind? ~ I'm afraid not.
But I will always think of you with
great affection
~ and wish you nothing but the best.
~ That sounds more final
than if you'd spat in my eye.
I love you, Isobel Crawley!
I know it's not enough.
I know I'm old and played-out.
But I do love you
with my whole heart.
You're not played-out!
And it means a great deal to me.
But I will not poison
what years we have left
by setting you against your
children.
Oh.
Have I interrupted a lovers' tryst?
Ha! Thank you for injecting humour
into this moment of misery.
~ I-I must go.
~ Oh, dear. I've cut you short.
Not really.
There was nothing more to say.
Goodbye.
That was rather sad.
Yes, it was sad.
~ Are we guests or servants tonight?
~ Both, I should hope!
I think we're as good as
the tenant farmers, thank you.
Mr Barrow, Andrew, they're starting
to arrive.
Mr Molesley can't manage on his own.
If you could bring up the food.
Yes, Mr Carson. Take those.
I wonder if I might have a word
later?
~ If such a thing were possible.
~ It's possible. Let me know when.
I thought it was a good moment,
while Mama has them all downstairs.
What are you thinking?
I'm taking photographs in my mind to
think of when I'm far away.
Oh, Tom.
I'm always ticking off Mary for
saying she doesn't want you to go,
but... I hope you know
how much I'll miss you.
I know how much I'll miss
all of you.
And I suppose that must be pretty
similar.
Great minds think alike.
What do you say we take a moment to
think of Sybil?
We're the three left on earth who
loved her the most.
And Mama and Papa.
~ But we're the three who should have
grown old with her. ~ That's true.
And who knows when we'll be together
again?
Darling Sybil.
Wherever you are...
.. we send you all our love and kisses
for the happiest of happy
Christmases.
Sybbie's last Christmas in this
house -
the house where she was born.
Don't say that. We'll be back.
You wouldn't consider leaving her
here until you'd settled in?
No, I would not.
No.
But I love the way you love her.
We must go down - they're arriving.
♪ Now to the Lord sing praises
♪ All you within this place
♪ And with true love and brotherhood
♪ Each other now embrace
♪ The holy tide of Christmas
♪ All others doth deface
♪ O tidings of comfort and joy
♪ Comfort and joy
♪ O tidings of comfort and joy ♪
We'll have a break now.
Please, all of you, help yourselves
to a drink
and have something to eat. You, too,
Molesley, Andrew.
Anna, you-you-you have a drink. I
want everybody to have a drink.
~ Some of us have already had a drink.
~ Don't be such a spoilsport.
~ What do you think you're doing?
~ God, you are a dreary little man.
~ Is everything going well here?
~ M'lady.
~ Spratt?
~ Yes.
Because I don't like dissension.
Spratt, I won't have it.
~ Dissension, m'Lady, perish the
thought. ~ Let's keep it that way.
~ You look very dazed.
~ I am.
You forget, I've never done
Christmas before.
~ At least not properly. ~ Well, you're
in for the Downton Christmas.
If that doesn't put you off, nothing
will.
It's funny,
it's finally beginning to sink in I
belong to two families.
~ I'm a part of both.
~ Me, too. It's called being married.
And I think it's just lovely.
~ Don't let Mr Carson catch you.
~ He seems a kind man to me.
He's a fair man, but I wouldn't put
it higher than that.
Thank you, Mrs Patmore.
Thank you.
Ooh. Close the door, for God's sake.
Make them think they're not allowed
in.
~ We can't stay for long - it's
cheating. ~ We have earned it.
~ After the year we've had.
~ Oh, I know.
Proposals and propositions.
Not what one expects at our age.
Oh, but I do wish you'd tell me the
truth about Princess Kuragin.
You detest her,
yet I've never known you fight for
anyone with more passion.
I suppose they're in Paris now, so
what harm can it do?
When I met the prince at the royal
wedding, we fell madly in love.
And in the weeks that followed -
weeks of balls and midnight skating
to the strains of the balalaika -
we resolved to elope.
~ You know, to be free.
~ And what happened?
Well, at the appointed hour,
we started for the port,
to set sail in the prince's yacht,
but...
.. my maid had betrayed us to the
princess,
who set out in pursuit.
She caught up with our carriage,
wrenched the door open
and pulled me out.
~ Pulled you out? By your arm?
~ Oh, by my arm, by my hair,
by my leg, anything to get me out of
the coach.
Then... she flung me into the cab
that brought her
and sent me back to Lord Grantham.
~ You must have looked rather
dishevelled. ~ Men notice nothing.
~ So she saved you from ruin.
~ From ruin...
.. from the loss of my children
and from a life in the shadows.
And you were grateful?
Within a week, I felt she had pulled
me back from the brink of the abyss.
And now, at last, you see,
we are even.
She saved me.
And I saved her.
And you've never strayed again?
~ I've never risked everything again.
~ It's not quite what I asked.
It's all the answer you'll get.
Remember, we were the Edwardians.
What are you doing hiding in here?
Quick! Come out. Chop, chop!
~ I suppose you're all packed?
~ Pretty well.
But you and I should go through
everything in my office.
~ In fact, you should take it over.
~ I wouldn't know where to start.
There's nothing I do you won't be
able to manage twice as well.
Tom, Mary, you have to come. Robert's
about to give a speech
~ and it is not a good idea.
~ It was bound to happen.
~ He hasn't touched a drop for months.
~ Ladies and gentlemen!
Ladies and gentlemen! I hope you
will let me speak for you
when I thank His Lordship for this
wonderful party
~ and for a marvellous year.
~ Now, just a minute...
♪ For he's a jolly good fellow
~ ♪ For he's a jolly good fellow
~ Is this a good moment?
It is if you want it to be.
♪.. fellow
♪ And so say all of us
And now Lady Mary is going to sing
for us,
accompanied by Lady Edith.
~ Do I have to?
~ Yes. ~ Oh.
♪ Silent night
♪ Holy night
♪ Sleeps the world, hid from sight
♪ Mary and Joseph in stable bare
♪ Watched o'er the child
♪ Beloved and fair
♪ Sleep in heavenly rest
♪ Sleep in heavenly rest ♪
~ I don't think I should.
~ Go on! It's Christmas.
Let's toast your new house.
Maybe I should mention one thing.
You say...'your new house', but it
isn't only mine.
~ No?
~ No.
I've registered it in both of our
names.
I hope you don't mind,
but I hate to change a plan when
there's no need.
Mr Carson, I'm very appreciative,
really,
~ but I can't accept.
~ Why not?
Who knows what the future may hold?
Or how much longer we'll even be
here?
Suppose you want to... move away and
change your life entirely.
You don't want to be stuck with me.
But that's the point.
What is?
I do want to be stuck with you.
I'm not convinced I can be hearing
this right.
You are, if you think I'm asking you
to marry me.
Well?
Well...
You could knock me down
with a feather.
And you're not offended?
Oh, Mr Carson,...
.. I can assure you
the very last thing in the world
that I am at this moment is offended.
You can take as long as you like -
I won't press you.
Because one thing I do know -
I'm not marrying anyone else.
Well, then.
What exactly are we celebrating?
We're celebrating the fact that I can
still get a proposal at my age.
And that's... it?
Of course I'll marry you,
you old booby.
I thought you'd never ask.
Hello, my darling.
We're going to miss you very much,
my boy.
Did I tell you? Very much.
~ I suppose everyone's saying that.
~ Yes, they are.
But it's not like you to be
sentimental.
In vino veritas - 'from
wine comes truth'.
The fact is, I've grown extremely
fond of you, Tom.
Sybil would be amazed to hear it
but I have.
Always remember you have a home to
come back to.
Sybil will be very touched. As am I.
And, yes, I will think of Downton as
my home.
And that would have amazed Sybil,
I've no doubt about it.
Now, what should Marigold call me?
Donk!
Why not? Everyone else does.
She can call me Donk and every time
she does, I'll be reminded of you.
Brava, Sybbie - that's a victory.
~ Oh, is it time to sing?
~ No.
No, I do have something to say.
Ladies and gentlemen.
My son-in-law, Mr Branson, asked for
your gratitude to me.
Now, Her Ladyship and I should like
to repay the compliment.
Tom Branson has helped Downton
navigate the choppy seas
of the modern world and brought it
to the good place where it is now.
But it is time for him to leave us.
And while we regret his going,
we wish him and Miss Sybbie well
in their new life.
So, let us give a round of applause
as a send-off.
~ Bravo.
~ ♪ O Come All Ye Faithful
Well done, but you didn't sound
drunk. How did you do that?
Concentration. You forget,
I was trained as a soldier.
♪ O come ye, O come ye to Bethlehem
♪ Come and behold Him
♪ Born the King of Angels
♪ O come, let us adore Him
~ ♪ O come, let us adore Him...
~ Mr Bates!
♪ O come, let us adore Him
♪ Christ the Lord
♪ God of God...
(Happy Christmas.)
♪ Lo, he abhors
♪ Not the virgin's womb
~ But how have you -
~ Shh.
We'll worry about everything else
later.
But for now, let's just have a very
happy Christmas.
♪ O come, let us adore Him
♪ Christ the Lord ♪